<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
 <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    category="std"
    docName="draft-abinabraham-vrrp-unicast-01"
    ipr="trust200902"
    submissionType="IETF"
    sortRefs="true"
    symRefs="true"
    tocDepth="3"
    tocInclude="true"
    updates="9568"
    version="3"
    xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Unicast VRRP">Unicast Support for the Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP)</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-abinabraham-vrrp-unicast-01"/>
    <author initials="A" surname="Dogra" fullname="Aditya Dogra">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sarjapur Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>addogra@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A" surname="Abraham" fullname="Abin Abraham">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sarjapur Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>abiabrah@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S" surname="Krishnamurthy" fullname="Seshan Krishnamurthy">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sarjapur Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>seshakri@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="14" month="May" year="2026"/>
    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <keyword>VRRP</keyword>
    <keyword>unicast</keyword>
    <keyword>first-hop redundancy</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        The Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP) Version 3 is specified
        for multicast operation on a shared LAN in RFC 9568. Some deployments
        require the VRRP first-hop redundancy function but cannot use
        multicast delivery for VRRP advertisements. This document updates RFC
        9568 by defining an optional configured unicast mode for VRRP Version
        3.
      </t>
      <t>
        In unicast mode, VRRP advertisements are sent to configured peer
        addresses rather than to the VRRP multicast group. Multicast mode
        remains the default mode. This document preserves the VRRP packet
        format, protocol number, virtual IP semantics, Virtual Router MAC
        behavior, and host-facing forwarding behavior defined in RFC 9568,
        while adding explicit peer configuration and receive-side source
        validation for unicast operation. YANG data model augmentation is
        deferred until the VRRP YANG bis work is stable.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC9568"/> specifies VRRP Version 3 for IPv4 and IPv6
        and assumes multicast operation on a shared LAN. In a number of
        deployments, redundant routers still need fast active/backup failover
        for a virtual default gateway, but the environment does not provide
        usable multicast support for VRRP advertisements.
      </t>
      <t>
        The primary deployment driver is the continued need for the classic
        VRRPv3 function of protecting a virtual IPv4 or IPv6 first-hop gateway
        in environments where multicast delivery is unavailable, undesirable,
        or operationally constrained. This includes virtualized, cloud,
        overlay, and other deployments in which Virtual Routers still provide
        a common host-facing gateway service, but control traffic between the
        Virtual Routers is exchanged through explicit peer connectivity
        instead of a simple multicast-capable LAN.
      </t>
      <t>
        The intended use case for this document is not a generic active/backup
        role-election mechanism. Rather, it is a narrow extension of VRRPv3 for
        deployments that want to preserve the familiar VRRP state machine,
        protocol number, virtual IP address semantics, Virtual Router MAC
        behavior, and host-facing forwarding model while using a different
        advertisement mode.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="req-lang">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
      <t>
        The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and
        "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
        when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="scope">
      <name>Scope and Applicability</name>
      <t>
        This document updates <xref target="RFC9568"/> by defining an
        optional configured unicast mode of operation for VRRPv3. Multicast
        mode remains the default mode of operation. The unicast mode is
        intended for deployments that still want the classic VRRP model of a
        Virtual Router protecting one or more virtual IPv4 or IPv6 addresses,
        but that cannot rely on multicast delivery of advertisements.
      </t>
      <t>
        The unicast mode defined here is limited to deployments in which the
        participating VRRP Routers can exchange advertisements without
        traversing a router that decrements the IPv4 TTL or IPv6 Hop Limit.
        This preserves the receive-side validation model of
        <xref target="RFC9568"/> and keeps the security and topology
        assumptions close to those of the base protocol.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document does not define multi-hop operation. If a deployment
        requires routed multi-hop active/backup election or transport
        encapsulation other than IP protocol 112, that deployment is outside
        the scope of this specification.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document does not update VRRP Version 2.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="usecases">
      <name>Use Cases and Deployment Drivers</name>
      <t>
        The operational motivation for unicast VRRP is straightforward:
        operators still need the classic VRRP function of protecting a virtual
        IPv4 or IPv6 default gateway, but some modern deployments cannot rely
        on multicast delivery for VRRP advertisements.
      </t>
      <t>
        Typical use cases include:
      </t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>
          <t>
            Cloud and virtualized environments in which multicast is not
            available or is not exposed in a way that is operationally
            equivalent to a simple shared LAN.
          </t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>
            Overlay or virtualized edge deployments in which the protected
            routers still present a common host-facing gateway service, but the
            control traffic between the routers is exchanged using explicit
            peer connectivity rather than a multicast-capable LAN.
          </t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>
            Service-provider and data-center designs in which operators want to
            preserve the familiar VRRP packet format, state machine, and
            virtual IP semantics of <xref target="RFC9568"/> while using a
            different advertisement mode.
          </t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>
        This document addresses those use cases by defining a unicast
        advertisement mode that stays close to the original VRRP model. It
        does not attempt to standardize broader routed active/backup election
        mechanisms that are no longer centered on protecting a virtual
        first-hop gateway.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="definitions">
      <name>Additional Definitions</name>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal" indent="24">
        <dt>Unicast Mode</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            A mode of VRRP operation in which advertisements for a Virtual
            Router are sent as unicast IPv4 or IPv6 packets to configured peer
            addresses instead of to the VRRP multicast destination address.
          </t>
        </dd>
        <dt>Unicast Peer</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            A configured VRRP Router participating in the same Virtual Router
            and address family whose address is used as a permitted source and
            destination for unicast VRRP advertisements.
          </t>
        </dd>
        <dt>Unicast Peer List</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            The configured set of all other VRRP Routers that participate in a
            unicast-mode Virtual Router for a given address family.
          </t>
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview">
      <name>Unicast VRRP Overview</name>
      <t>
        A Virtual Router defined by this document operates in exactly one of
        two advertisement modes:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>multicast mode, as specified in <xref target="RFC9568"/>, or</li>
        <li>unicast mode, as specified in this document.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        Multicast mode is the default mode. A VRRP Router
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use multicast mode unless unicast mode is
        explicitly configured for the Virtual Router.
      </t>
      <t>
        A VRRP Router operating a given Virtual Router in unicast mode
        <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> send VRRP advertisements for that Virtual
        Router to the VRRP multicast destination address. Instead, it
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> send a copy of each advertisement to each address
        in the configured Unicast Peer List.
      </t>
      <t>
        Except as updated by this document, the VRRP packet format, VRRP
        state machine, timer calculations, preemption behavior, Virtual Router
        semantics, virtual IP address behavior, and host-facing forwarding
        behavior remain as specified in <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Unicast mode is configured per Virtual Router.
        A VRRP Router <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> mix multicast mode and unicast
        mode for the same Virtual Router instance.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="peer-config">
      <name>Peer Configuration</name>
      <t>
        A Virtual Router operating in unicast mode <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        configured with one or more Unicast Peers. A configuration that
        enables unicast mode without at least one peer is invalid, and the
        Virtual Router <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> operate in unicast mode until
        corrected.
      </t>
      <t>
        Each VRRP Router participating in a unicast-mode Virtual Router
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be configured with the addresses of all other
        participating VRRP Routers for that Virtual Router and address family.
      </t>
      <t>
        For IPv4 operation, each configured peer address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        be an IPv4 address that the receiving peer uses as the source address
        for VRRP advertisements, as described in
        <xref target="ipv4-fields"/>. For IPv6 operation, each configured peer
        address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be an IPv6 link-local address used by the
        receiving peer as the source address for VRRP advertisements, as
        described in <xref target="ipv6-fields"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        The local router's own address <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear in its
        Unicast Peer List.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rfc9568-updates">
      <name>Updates to RFC 9568</name>
      <section anchor="overview-update">
        <name>VRRP Overview</name>
        <t>
          The references to multicast-only operation in
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="3" sectionFormat="of"/> are updated
          to allow an advertisement to be delivered either to the VRRP
          multicast destination address, as specified in
          <xref target="RFC9568"/>, or to configured Unicast Peers, as
          specified in this document.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="protocol-update">
        <name>Protocol Processing</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="5" sectionFormat="of"/> is updated
          so that a Virtual Router operating in unicast mode sends and
          receives VRRP advertisements only through the configured Unicast Peer
          List for that Virtual Router and address family.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ipv4-fields">
        <name>IPv4 Field Descriptions</name>
        <t>
          For a Virtual Router operating in unicast mode, the IPv4 field
          descriptions in <xref target="RFC9568" section="5.1.1"
          sectionFormat="of"/> are updated as follows:
        </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv4 source address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the primary IPv4
              address of the sending interface, as specified in
              <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv4 destination address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the IPv4
              address of the configured Unicast Peer to which the copy of the
              advertisement is being sent.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv4 TTL <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 255, and a received
              packet whose IPv4 TTL is not 255 <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              discarded.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv4 Protocol field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> remain 112.
            </t>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ipv6-fields">
        <name>IPv6 Field Descriptions</name>
        <t>
          For a Virtual Router operating in unicast mode, the IPv6 field
          descriptions in <xref target="RFC9568" section="5.1.2"
          sectionFormat="of"/> are updated as follows:
        </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv6 source address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the link-local
              address of the sending interface, as specified in
              <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv6 destination address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the
              configured IPv6 link-local address of the Unicast Peer to which
              the copy of the advertisement is being sent.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv6 Hop Limit <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to 255, and a
              received packet whose Hop Limit is not 255 <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
              be discarded.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              The IPv6 Next Header field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> remain 112.
            </t>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tx-update">
        <name>Transmitting VRRP Packets</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="7.2" sectionFormat="of"/> is updated
          so that a VRRP Router operating a Virtual Router in unicast mode
          sends one copy of each VRRP advertisement to each configured Unicast
          Peer instead of sending the advertisement to the VRRP multicast
          group.
        </t>
        <t>
          Other than the destination address, the packet contents
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the same for each transmitted copy.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="rx-update">
        <name>Receiving VRRP Packets</name>
        <t>
          A VRRP Router operating a Virtual Router in unicast mode
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> process only advertisements whose source address
          matches an address in the configured Unicast Peer List for that
          Virtual Router and address family.
        </t>
        <t>
          A received VRRP packet for a unicast-mode Virtual Router
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be discarded if:
        </t>
        <ul spacing="normal">
          <li>the source address is not a configured Unicast Peer,</li>
          <li>the IPv4 TTL or IPv6 Hop Limit is not 255,</li>
          <li>the packet is received for the wrong address family, or</li>
          <li>the packet is otherwise invalid according to <xref target="RFC9568"/>.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          A VRRP Router operating a Virtual Router in unicast mode
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore VRRP advertisements for that same Virtual
          Router received through multicast delivery.
        </t>
        <t>
          A VRRP Router operating a Virtual Router in multicast mode
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore unicast VRRP advertisements for that same
          Virtual Router.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="host-facing-update">
        <name>Host-Facing Behavior</name>
        <t>
          This document changes only advertisement delivery. The Active
          Router's behavior with respect to the Virtual Router MAC address,
          ARP, gratuitous ARP, IPv6 Neighbor Discovery, Router
          Advertisements, Unsolicited Neighbor Advertisements, and forwarding
          responsibility remains as specified in <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          In particular, unicast mode does not replace the Virtual Router MAC
          with a multicast MAC. The Virtual Router MAC remains the well-known
          unicast VRRP MAC associated with the VRID, as specified in
          <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="operational">
      <name>Operational Considerations</name>
      <t>
        A deployment using unicast mode <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> ensure that all
        routers in a given Virtual Router are configured with a consistent
        peer inventory. Inconsistent peer lists can create asymmetric
        reachability and can lead to multiple routers independently deciding
        that the Active Router has failed.
      </t>
      <t>
        A deployment using unicast mode <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> continue to use
        distinct priority values as recommended in <xref target="RFC9568"/> so
        that Backup Routers do not transition to Active state simultaneously
        after a failure.
      </t>
      <t>
        <xref target="yang-considerations"/> describes the intended YANG
        model alignment for unicast-mode configuration and operational state.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="yang-considerations">
      <name>YANG Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document does not define a YANG module. The VRRP YANG data model
        is currently being revised by
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-vrrp-rfc8347bis"/>, which is intended to
        obsolete <xref target="RFC8347"/>. Deferring the unicast VRRP YANG
        augmentation until that work is approved or published allows the
        augmentation to be based on the stable successor to
        <xref target="RFC8347"/>, avoids unnecessary churn against a moving
        base model, and helps ensure alignment with the final VRRP YANG
        schema.
      </t>
      <t>
        A future revision of this document, or a companion YANG document, is
        expected to define the management model for configuring the VRRP
        advertisement mode, the unicast peer list, and related operational
        state after <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-vrrp-rfc8347bis"/> has been
        approved or published as an RFC.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        The security considerations of <xref target="RFC9568"/> continue to
        apply. In particular, VRRP still provides no confidentiality and does
        not prevent a hostile node from attempting to act as an Active Router.
      </t>
      <t>
        Unicast mode introduces explicit peer configuration and requires that
        a receiver validate the source address against the configured Unicast
        Peer List. This provides an additional filtering mechanism beyond the
        receive-side IPv4 TTL or IPv6 Hop Limit check.
      </t>
      <t>
        Because this document preserves the requirement that the IPv4 TTL or
        IPv6 Hop Limit be 255 on transmitted and accepted packets, the
        protection against packets arriving from a remote network described in
        <xref target="RFC5082"/> continues to apply.
      </t>
      <t>
        A future specification for multi-hop unicast operation would need a
        different security model and is outside the scope of this document.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document requests no IANA actions.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119">
          <front>
            <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
            <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="1997"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC8174" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174">
          <front>
            <title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="Barry Leiba">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="May" year="2017"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8174"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC9568" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9568">
          <front>
            <title>Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP) Version 3 for IPv4 and IPv6</title>
            <author initials="A." surname="Lindem" fullname="Acee Lindem">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Dogra" fullname="Aditya Dogra">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="April" year="2024"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9568"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9568"/>
        </reference>

      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC8347" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8347">
          <front>
            <title>A YANG Data Model for the Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP)</title>
            <author initials="X." surname="Liu" fullname="Xufeng Liu" role="editor">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Kyparlis" fullname="Athanasios Kyparlis">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="R." surname="Parikh" fullname="Ravi Parikh">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Lindem" fullname="Acee Lindem">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="M." surname="Zhang" fullname="Mingui Zhang">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="March" year="2018"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8347"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8347"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-vrrp-rfc8347bis" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-rtgwg-vrrp-rfc8347bis/">
          <front>
            <title>A YANG Data Model for the Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP)</title>
            <author initials="A." surname="Lindem" fullname="Acee Lindem">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date day="13" month="February" year="2026"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-rtgwg-vrrp-rfc8347bis-15"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC5082" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5082">
          <front>
            <title>The Generalized TTL Security Mechanism (GTSM)</title>
            <author initials="V." surname="Gill" fullname="Vijay Gill">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Heasley" fullname="Jeffrey Heasley">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Meyer" fullname="David Meyer">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="October" year="2007"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5082"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5082"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
