<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
 <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    category="info"
    consensus="false"
    docName="draft-abinabraham-vrrp-unicast-deployment-00"
    ipr="trust200902"
    submissionType="IETF"
    sortRefs="true"
    symRefs="true"
    tocDepth="3"
    tocInclude="true"
    version="3"
    xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Unicast VRRP Overview">Deployment Experience and Considerations for Unicast VRRP</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-abinabraham-vrrp-unicast-deployment-00"/>
    <author initials="A" surname="Dogra" fullname="Aditya Dogra">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sarjapur Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <email>addogra@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A" surname="Abraham" fullname="Abin Abraham">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sarjapur Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91 80 4426 7078</phone>
        <email>abiabrah@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S" surname="Krishnamurthy" fullname="Seshan Krishnamurthy">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sarjapur Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560103</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91 80 4429 2149</phone>
        <email>seshakri@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="11" month="April" year="2026"/>
    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <keyword>VRRP</keyword>
    <keyword>unicast</keyword>
    <keyword>first-hop redundancy</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document surveys deployed approaches to operating the Virtual
        Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP) over unicast transport in
        environments where the multicast assumptions of RFC 9568
        are unavailable, undesirable, or operationally constrained. The
        document summarizes implementation patterns seen in public
        documentation, highlights common configuration and operational themes,
        and identifies interoperability gaps between deployed approaches.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document does not define a new interoperable unicast VRRP
        protocol. Instead, it records deployment experience and outlines the
        areas that would need to be addressed by any future standards-track
        extension to VRRP.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC9568"/> defines version 3 of the Virtual Router
        Redundancy Protocol (VRRP) for IPv4 and IPv6. VRRP provides a
        first-hop redundancy mechanism in which multiple routers cooperate so
        that one router, the Active Router, forwards traffic for a protected
        virtual router while one or more Backup Routers stand by to take over
        if needed.
      </t>
      <t>
        The deployed environment for first-hop redundancy has evolved. Many
        service-provider, cloud, overlay, and virtualized environments either
        do not support the multicast delivery model assumed by
        <xref target="RFC9568"/> or do not expose it in a form that is
        operationally equivalent to a classic shared LAN. As a result, several
        implementations now support some form of "unicast VRRP".
      </t>
      <t>
        Public documentation shows that these implementations do not all make
        the same design choices. Some preserve the traditional VRRP gateway
        protection model and primarily replace multicast advertisement delivery
        with configured unicast peers. Others use VRRP-derived state exchange
        to solve a broader routed active/backup role-selection problem.
      </t>
      <t>
        The purpose of this document is to capture that deployment experience
        and describe where the common ground ends. This provides a basis for
        discussing whether future standardization should focus on a minimal
        unicast transport extension for VRRP, a richer multi-peer unicast
        profile, or a separate active/standby election mechanism for routed
        environments.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="scope">
      <name>Scope and Non-Goals</name>
      <t>
        This document is informational. It documents publicly visible industry
        practice and the resulting design space. It is not a protocol
        specification and it does not update <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
      </t>
      <t>This document has the following goals:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>describe the multicast and LAN assumptions in <xref target="RFC9568"/>,</li>
        <li>summarize deployed unicast VRRP implementation models,</li>
        <li>highlight operational and interoperability differences, and</li>
        <li>identify the sections of <xref target="RFC9568"/> that would likely need revision in a future standards-track effort.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>This document intentionally does not:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>claim interoperability among deployed unicast implementations,</li>
        <li>specify a new wire protocol, or</li>
        <li>declare one vendor-specific implementation model to be the standard.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section anchor="baseline">
      <name>Standards Baseline</name>
      <t>
        The starting point for any discussion of unicast VRRP is the protocol
        model in <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="baseline-rfc9568">
        <name>Assumptions in RFC 9568</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC9568"/> specifies VRRP operation on a shared LAN.
          VRRP advertisements are sent to the well-known VRRP multicast
          destination addresses for IPv4 and IPv6, and receive-side processing
          checks the IPv4 TTL or IPv6 Hop Limit to ensure that the packet has
          not traversed a remote network.
        </t>
        <t>
          The protocol is also tightly coupled to the use of a Virtual Router
          MAC address and to host-facing ARP or Neighbor Discovery behavior
          associated with first-hop gateway protection on a shared segment.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="baseline-drivers">
        <name>Deployment Drivers for Unicast Operation</name>
        <t>
          Operators increasingly deploy redundant routers in routed, overlay,
          and virtualized environments where native LAN multicast is not
          available or is operationally inconvenient. Public cloud is one
          example, but the details matter. Azure Virtual Network explicitly
          supports only unicast traffic within the virtual network
          <xref target="AZURE-VNET-FAQ"/>, while AWS supports multicast through
          Transit Gateway multicast rather than through the simple on-link model
          assumed by classic VRRP <xref target="AWS-TGW-MCAST"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          In these environments, operators still want fast failure detection
          and deterministic active/backup behavior for one or more protected
          addresses, prefixes, or route-owner roles. This operational demand is
          the primary reason unicast VRRP variants have emerged.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="survey">
      <name>Survey of Deployed Unicast VRRP Approaches</name>
      <t>
        This section summarizes implementation behavior described in publicly
        available documentation. The absence of a feature in this survey only
        means that it was not found in the referenced public documentation.
      </t>
      <section anchor="survey-models">
        <name>Common Design Families</name>
        <t>
          The published implementations reviewed by the authors fit roughly
          into three families:
        </t>
        <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
          <li>
            <t>
              A transport-replacement model in which VRRP largely preserves its
              role as a first-hop redundancy mechanism while advertisement
              delivery is changed from multicast to configured unicast peers.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              A multi-peer unicast model in which multiple peers can be
              configured explicitly and additional source or TTL validation
              controls are provided.
            </t>
          </li>
          <li>
            <t>
              A routed active/backup election model in which VRRP-derived
              protocol elements are used for role selection across a Layer 3
              network and not always for classic host-facing gateway
              protection.
            </t>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section anchor="survey-table">
        <name>Examples from Public Documentation</name>
        <table anchor="tab-support">
          <name>Examples of deployed unicast VRRP behavior</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Implementation</th>
              <th>Unicast support found</th>
              <th>Peer model</th>
              <th>Operational notes</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>Cisco IOS XR</td>
              <td>Yes</td>
              <td>Two-node unicast peer model</td>
              <td>Preserves VIP-centric first-hop redundancy behavior and disables multicast VRRP when unicast is configured <xref target="CISCO-XR-VRRP"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Huawei VRP</td>
              <td>Yes</td>
              <td>Two-node routed peer model</td>
              <td>Documents a proprietary VRRPv2-based unicast mode, configurable UDP port usage, optional authentication, and semantics that differ from common VRRP gateway protection <xref target="HUAWEI-UC-VRRP"/> <xref target="HUAWEI-UC-VRRP-PORT"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Keepalived</td>
              <td>Yes</td>
              <td>Multi-peer unicast model</td>
              <td>Supports peer lists, source validation, and TTL controls; also notes that unicast peers are outside strict RFC behavior <xref target="KEEPALIVED"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>VyOS</td>
              <td>Yes</td>
              <td>Peer-based unicast model</td>
              <td>Supports explicit peer and source configuration and an optional compatibility mode closer to classic VRRP semantics <xref target="VYOS-HA"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Juniper Cloud-Native Router</td>
              <td>Yes</td>
              <td>Cloud active/backup role model</td>
              <td>Documents unicast VRRP in cloud workflows and uses VRRP state to influence route-table ownership in AWS-oriented deployments <xref target="JUNIPER-CNR-VRRP"/> <xref target="JUNIPER-CNR-EKS"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>MikroTik RouterOS</td>
              <td>Not found</td>
              <td>Classic shared-segment VRRP</td>
              <td>Public documentation reviewed by the authors remains aligned with multicast VRRP behavior <xref target="MIKROTIK-VRRP"/></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>FRRouting</td>
              <td>Not found</td>
              <td>Classic shared-segment VRRP</td>
              <td>Public documentation reviewed by the authors describes VRRPv2 and VRRPv3 behavior on Linux without documenting a unicast mode <xref target="FRR-VRRP"/></td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="themes">
      <name>Common Protocol and Operational Themes</name>
      <section anchor="themes-peers">
        <name>Configured Peers</name>
        <t>
          Every deployed unicast approach reviewed by the authors replaces
          passive discovery through multicast reception with some form of
          explicit peer configuration. The most basic form is a single
          configured peer address for a two-node deployment. Other
          implementations support a list of peers and optional source address
          configuration.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="themes-transport">
        <name>Packet Transport</name>
        <t>
          The reviewed implementations do not all converge on one transport
          model. Some are described as unicast delivery of VRRP
          advertisements, while Huawei documents a VRRPv2-based proprietary
          unicast mode with a configurable UDP port. This is a significant
          interoperability fault line because not all implementations appear to
          preserve the exact packet and transport assumptions of
          <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="themes-ttl">
        <name>TTL and Hop-Limit Validation</name>
        <t>
          The receive-side IPv4 TTL or IPv6 Hop Limit check in
          <xref target="RFC9568"/> is a core part of VRRP's LAN-scoped security
          model. Deployed unicast implementations preserve this logic to
          varying degrees. Some preserve the value 255 check, some expose
          minimum and maximum TTL controls, and some rely more heavily on
          source address validation because the protected peers are no longer
          confined to one simple shared segment.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="themes-vmac">
        <name>Virtual MAC, ARP, and Neighbor Discovery Behavior</name>
        <t>
          Deployed implementations differ on whether unicast VRRP is still
          fundamentally a host-facing first-hop redundancy mechanism. In the
          conservative transport-replacement model, the Virtual Router MAC
          address, ARP behavior, gratuitous ARP, and IPv6 Neighbor Discovery
          logic remain important. In more routed active/backup models, the role
          of a Virtual Router MAC address may be reduced or the first-hop
          gateway semantics may no longer be the primary objective.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="themes-role">
        <name>VIP Protection versus Role Selection</name>
        <t>
          The most important semantic split in the deployment space is whether
          "unicast VRRP" is being used to protect a virtual first-hop address
          or to perform a broader active/backup role election across a Layer 3
          topology. The former use case is much closer to the original VRRP
          model. The latter use case may still reuse VRRP concepts and state,
          but it stretches beyond the assumptions of <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="themes-management">
        <name>Management Considerations</name>
        <t>
          Publicly documented unicast implementations expose additional knobs
          beyond those needed for multicast VRRP. Examples include peer lists,
          source-address pinning, TTL or hop-limit validation policy, transport
          selection, and unicast-specific authentication. These are not modeled
          by the current base VRRP specification and would need explicit
          treatment in any future management model update.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="interop">
      <name>Interoperability Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document does not assume that the deployed implementations
        summarized above interoperate on the wire. In fact, the reviewed public
        documentation strongly suggests that interoperability should not be
        assumed.
      </t>
      <t>
        The main interoperability gaps are:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>pairwise versus multi-peer operation,</li>
        <li>differences in packet transport,</li>
        <li>different receive-side source and TTL validation models,</li>
        <li>different expectations around the Virtual Router MAC address, ARP, and Neighbor Discovery, and</li>
        <li>different problem statements, namely first-hop gateway protection versus routed active/backup role selection.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        For that reason, the most accurate near-term framing for unicast VRRP
        is a family of deployment techniques rather than a single interoperable
        extension of <xref target="RFC9568"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="future">
      <name>Considerations for Future Standardization</name>
      <t>
        The deployment experience summarized in this document suggests three
        possible directions for future work:
      </t>
      <ol spacing="normal" type="1">
        <li>
          <t>
            A minimal extension that preserves VRRP packet semantics and
            first-hop redundancy behavior while replacing multicast delivery
            with configured unicast peers.
          </t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>
            A richer unicast VRRP profile that standardizes peer lists, source
            validation, and multi-peer behavior.
          </t>
        </li>
        <li>
          <t>
            A separate active/backup election mechanism for routed
            environments, if the working group concludes that the routed role
            selection use case should not be forced into the classic VRRP
            model.
          </t>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <t>
        Whichever direction is chosen, it would need to make an explicit
        decision about scope. A future document should not try to standardize
        all observed deployment styles at once unless it is prepared to define
        multiple profiles with clear interoperability expectations.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC9568"/> relies in part on the IPv4 TTL or IPv6
        Hop Limit value of 255 to keep attacks scoped to the local network
        <xref target="RFC5082"/>. Moving VRRP-like behavior to unicast
        environments can change that threat model, especially when peers are
        separated by one or more routed hops or when the protected role is no
        longer limited to host-facing gateway service on a LAN.
      </t>
      <t>
        Publicly documented implementations respond to this in different ways,
        including explicit peer allow-lists, configured source addresses, TTL
        or hop-limit range checks, and vendor-specific authentication. These
        mitigations improve robustness, but they also show that deployed
        unicast approaches do not currently share a single security model.
      </t>
      <t>
        Any future standards-track unicast VRRP specification would need to
        define a precise peer trust model, specify how receive-side validation
        is performed, and describe what protections are expected when the
        protocol operates beyond a single shared LAN.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="rfc9568-touchpoints" numbered="false">
      <name>Appendix A. Candidate RFC 9568 Touchpoints for a Future Protocol Specification</name>
      <t>
        The brainstorming for this work identified several parts of
        <xref target="RFC9568"/> that would likely need review if the community
        later decides to standardize a unicast extension rather than only
        document deployment experience.
      </t>
      <section anchor="touch-definitions" numbered="false">
        <name>Definitions</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="1.7" sectionFormat="of"/> defines
          the Virtual Router MAC address in terms that are tightly linked to
          VRRP advertisement delivery. A future unicast protocol specification
          would likely need to clarify whether the Virtual Router MAC address
          remains mandatory, optional, or orthogonal to advertisement delivery.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="touch-overview" numbered="false">
        <name>Overview and Protocol Description</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="3" sectionFormat="of"/> and
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="5" sectionFormat="of"/> explicitly
          describe VRRP in multicast terms. A future standards-track document
          would need to state whether unicast operation is a separate mode,
          whether it changes the topology assumptions, and what remains common
          across multicast and unicast operation.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="touch-ip-fields" numbered="false">
        <name>IPv4 and IPv6 Field Descriptions</name>
        <t>
          The brainstormed protocol impact points align with
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="5.1.1" sectionFormat="of"/> and
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="5.1.2" sectionFormat="of"/>. A
          future protocol specification would need to revisit destination
          addressing, source-address selection, and how the TTL or Hop Limit
          checks apply in routed or peer-configured deployments.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="touch-transmit" numbered="false">
        <name>Transmit Rules</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC9568" section="7.2" sectionFormat="of"/> instructs
          a sender to transmit to the VRRP IPv4 or IPv6 multicast group. Any
          interoperable unicast protocol specification would need to replace
          this with clear peer-selection and destination-addressing rules.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <reference anchor="RFC9568" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc9568">
          <front>
            <title>Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol (VRRP) Version 3 for IPv4 and IPv6</title>
            <author initials="A." surname="Lindem" fullname="Acee Lindem">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="A." surname="Dogra" fullname="Aditya Dogra">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="April" year="2024"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="9568"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC9568"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC5082" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5082">
          <front>
            <title>The Generalized TTL Security Mechanism (GTSM)</title>
            <author initials="V." surname="Gill" fullname="Vijay Gill">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Heasley" fullname="Jeffrey Heasley">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Meyer" fullname="David Meyer">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="October" year="2007"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5082"/>
          <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5082"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="AWS-TGW-MCAST" target="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/vpc/latest/tgw/tgw-multicast-overview.html">
          <front>
            <title>Multicast for Transit Gateways</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Amazon Web Services</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="AZURE-VNET-FAQ" target="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-network/virtual-networks-faq#do-virtual-networks-support-multicast-or-broadcast">
          <front>
            <title>Azure Virtual Network FAQ</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Microsoft</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="CISCO-XR-VRRP" target="https://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/td/docs/routers/asr9000/software/asr9k-r7-9/ip-addresses/configuration/guide/b-ip-addresses-cg-asr9000-79x/implementing-vrrp.html">
          <front>
            <title>Implementing VRRP on Cisco IOS XR</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Includes a section on Unicast VRRP</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="FRR-VRRP" target="https://docs.frrouting.org/en/stable-7.5/vrrp.html">
          <front>
            <title>FRRouting VRRP</title>
            <author>
              <organization>FRRouting Project</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="HUAWEI-UC-VRRP">
          <front>
            <title>VRRP in Unicast Mode</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Huawei</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Huawei HedEx documentation, EDOC1100363264</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="HUAWEI-UC-VRRP-PORT">
          <front>
            <title>unicast-vrrp port Command Reference</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Huawei</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
          <refcontent>Huawei HedEx documentation, EDOC1100277644</refcontent>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="JUNIPER-CNR-EKS" target="https://www.juniper.net/documentation/us/en/software/cloud-native-router25.4/cloud-native-router-deployment-guide/topics/concept/system-resource-requirements-eks.html">
          <front>
            <title>Cloud-Native Router Deployment on Amazon EKS</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="JUNIPER-CNR-VRRP" target="https://www.juniper.net/documentation/us/en/software/cloud-native-router23.4/cloud-native-router-user/topics/concept/l3-vrrp.html">
          <front>
            <title>Cloud-Native Router VRRP Overview</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="KEEPALIVED" target="https://www.keepalived.org/manpage.html">
          <front>
            <title>keepalived.conf(5) Manpage</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Keepalived Project</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="MIKROTIK-VRRP" target="https://help.mikrotik.com/docs/spaces/ROS/pages/81362945/VRRP">
          <front>
            <title>RouterOS VRRP</title>
            <author>
              <organization>MikroTik</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="VYOS-HA" target="https://docs.vyos.io/en/1.4/configuration/highavailability/">
          <front>
            <title>VyOS High Availability</title>
            <author>
              <organization>VyOS Project</organization>
            </author>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
